Guide to the Robert L. Fisher Papers 1951-1989
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
Robert L. Fisher papers
1951-1989
1956-1971
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
4249
4249-001
Fisher, Robert L. (Robert Light), 1910-1989
3.04 cubic feet 5 boxes
Papers of an American official of the United Nations Relief and Works Agency primarily concerning his work in Jordan and Gaza during the late 1950s to early 1970s.
Robert Light Fisher was born in York, Pennsylvania, in 1910. He received his teaching credential from Western Washington Normal School, Bellingham, Washington, where his father, Charles Henry Fisher, had been president, and went on to receive degrees from Stanford and Columbia in political science. Fisher joined the State Department in 1940 and worked in the U.S. Army's Intelligence Section during World War II. After the war, he served as the Army's liaison for displaced persons in Europe. Fisher joined the United Nations' Commission for Displaced Arabs in the Middle East in the late 1940s and in 1950 was appointed its chair. In 1953 he became assistant director of the United Nations Relief and Works Agency for Palestine Refugees in the Near East (UNRWA) in Jordan, and in 1958 he was appointed director of the UNRWA in Gaza. In 1961 Fisher became director of UNRWA affairs in Jordon. He supervised the establishment of refugee camps and the building of schools and health centers. Fisher obtained a senior post at UNRWA headquarters in Beirut in 1968 and returned to the State Department in 1970. Upon his retirement in 1980, Fisher returned to the state of Washington, where he died in 1989.
Diaries, photographs, reports, newsletters, correspondence, cables, memos, clippings, publications, and news releases, 1951-1989 (bulk 1956-1971), concerning Fisher's work on behalf of the United Nations Relief and Works Agency for Palestine Refugees in the Near East.
The papers consist almost exclusively of materials relating to Fisher's work in Gaza and Jordan during the late 1950s to early 1970s, with some material from later years. The largest series is the subject series, which is organized according to Fisher's original topical scheme. Photocopies of deteriorating thermofaxes are filed with the original copies. A substantial number of photographs of UNRWA projects and events are included in the papers.
The papers are open to all users.
Gift of Helen S. Fisher (Robert L. Fisher's wife) of Lacey, Washington, 1991.
Official United Nations documents have been transferred to the Government Publications division of the University of Washington Libraries. Publications from the Institute for Palestine Studies have been transferred to the main collection of the UW Libraries.
Researchers interested in Robert L. Fisher's personal life may wish to consult the Charles Henry Fisher papers, Accession No. 1987-14, which consists of 49 letters from Robert Fisher's father during the time when he was field director of the UNRWA (1962-1964).
Fisher, Robert L. (Robert Light), 1910-1989--Archives
United Nations Relief and Works Agency for Palestine Refugees in the Near East
International relief; Palestinian Arabs--Services for; Political refugees--Services for--Middle East; Refugees, Palestinian Arab--Education; Refugees, Palestinian Arab--Jordan; Refugees, Palestinian Arab--Services for; United Nations--Officials and employees--Archives
International Relations; Photographs
Calendars; correspondence; Diaries; Newsletters; Photograph albums; Photographs; Press releases; Publications; reports
- Diaries and calendars, 1956-1958, 1964-1971 (Box 1-2)
- Biographical information, 1964-1990 (Box-folder 3/1)
- Biographical information - condolences, 1989 (Box-folder 3/2)
- Incoming letters, 1978 (Box-folder 3/3)
- Reports
  - United Nations Relief and Works Agency for Palestine Refugees in the Near East, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1986 (Box-folder 3/5)
- Speeches and writings, 1957-1968 (Box-folder 3/6)
- Photographs
  - "Official", 1967-1969 (Box-folder 3/7-8)
  - Jordan, 1965-1968 (Box-folder 3/9-13)
  - Miscellaneous, 1964-1976 (Box-folder 3/14-18)
  - Photo albums, 1954-1974 (Box 5)
- Organizational directives, 1959-1962 (Box-folder 3/19)
- Memo, 1964 (Box-folder 3/20)
- Subject series
  - Conciliation Commission for Palestine, 1962-1964 (Box-folder 3/21)
  - Confidential draft paper of 1958 (Box-folder 3/22)
  - Development Bank of Jordan, Ltd., 1951-1979 (Box-folder 3/23)
  - Gaza basic papers, 1960-1962 (Box-folder 3/24)
  - Humor, 1956-1960 (Box-folder 3/25)
  - Ideas, etc., 1959 (Box-folder 3/26)
  - Ideas for publications, 1969 (Box-folder 3/27)
  - Materials for articles, 1963 (Box-folder 3/28)
  - Middle East crisis, 1967 (Box-folder 3/29)
  - Problems facing UNRWA as it changes directors, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 3/30)
  - "The Refugee Problem", 1969 (Box-folder 3/31)
  - Refugee resettlement through the medium of individual grants in Jordan, 1960 (Box-folder 3/32)
  - Relations between UNRWA and UAR government, 1960-1961 (Box-folder 3/33)
  - Solution to the Palestine (refugee) problem, 1953-1967 (Box-folder 3/34)
  - Statistics, 1950-1973 (Box-folder 3/35)
  - Status of the Gaza mission, UNRWA, 1959 (Box-folder 3/36)
  - Transfer from Jordan to Beirut, 1968 (Box-folder 3/37)
  - United Nations Emergency Force - miscellaneous items, 1960-1961 (Box-folder 3/38)
  - West Bank data base project, 1984 (Box-folder 3/39)
  - Women's Auxiliary of UNRWA, 1958-1965 (Box-folder 3/40)
- Proceedings, 1978 (Box-folder 3/41)
- Hearings transcript - U.S. Senate Foreign Relations Committee, Near Eastern and South Asian Affairs Committee, 1976 (Box-folder 3/42)
- Ephemera, undated (Box-folder 3/43)
- Publications
  - UNRWA, undated (Box-folder 3/44)
  - American Friends Service Committee, 1958 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Middle East Institute, 1974 (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1956-1989 (Box-folder 4/3)
- Financial records, 1974-1978 (Box-folder 4/4)
- Newsletters
  - UNRWA, 1962-1986 (Box-folder 4/5)
  - Miscellaneous, 1974-1986 (Box-folder 4/6)
- News releases
  - UNRWA, 1968-1978 (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Miscellaneous, 1977 (Box-folder 4/8)
- Maps, 1955-1957 (Box-folder 4/9)
- Clippings, 1963-1978 (Box-folder 4/10)
- Miscellany, 1968 (Box-folder 4/11)